# **CHRISTOPHER RUIZ**

Tucson, AZ 85719 ◆ (520) 600-8302 ◆ CHRISRUIZAZ@gmail.com

https://chrisruizaz.github.io/PolishedPortfolio/ ◆ https://www.linkedin.com/in/christopher-ruiz-090444193/ ◆ https://github.com/chrisruizaz

## PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

5 years of experience in the automotive industry with customer service as well as automotive repair and maintenance. Obtained 6 certification in automotive repair and 2 certification in customer service through the Automotive Service Excellence program. 2 years of experience with security as well as Armed Guard Training. Full Stack Web Development through the University of Arizona Boot camp.

# **SKILLS**

- Automotive Customer Service Adviser
- Automotive repair
- Calculus
- Cashier
- Customer service
- Inventory
- Loss prevention
- Managing
- Note taking
- Radio
- Sales
- Spanish

- Estimate preparation
- Safety awareness
- Vehicle alignment
- Preventive maintenance
- Brake systems understanding
- Web development
- JavaScript experience
- Loss prevention and mitigation
- Defensive tactics
- Personnel and visitor searches
- Firearms expertise

#### WORK HISTORY

#### ASE Certified Technician, 03/2017 to 09/2019

#### BrakeMax – Tucson, AZ

- Automotive repair and maintenance specializing in: suspension, alignments, brakes, heating and air conditioning systems
- Some experience in diagnostics of: engine performance, drive train, air conditioning and electronic systems
- Obtained tools to minimize time spent on repairs and special tools for diagnostics

- Eager to learn new systems and repair techniques to maximize productivity while bringing a positive attitude to every situation
- Assessed vehicle maintenance status and completed mileage-based services, including changing out belts, filling fluids and replacing gaskets
- Completed computer-assigned vehicle alignments

#### Mechanic, 09/2014 to 03/2017

#### Goodyear – Tucson, AZ

- Began career as a mechanic at BrakeMax
- Left to pursue more training and opportunity at Goodyear Automotive as a tire installer and general service technician
- Gathered experience with alignments, suspension systems and brakes
- Obtained more tools and certifications to continue to pursue profession as an automotive technician
- Serviced vehicles according to OEM recommended maintenance schedules for oil changes, engine tune-ups and fluid changes
- Tested newly installed equipment to determine proper functionality and compliance with regulations
- Left Goodyear to briefly work at Pep Boys as a technician for an opportunity to receive training and more certifications

#### Customer Service Adviser, 11/2012 to 09/2014

#### **PepBoys** – Tucson, AZ

- Aiding customers with decisions on automotive repairs and maintenance
- Provided complete estimates with options for parts and accurate labor time, as well as future repairs
- Worked with a sense of urgency to provide customers and technicians information in a timely manor while keeping a positive rapport between the two
- Obtained two certification for customer service and received a promotion to a manger position
- As a manager I hired technicians, service advisers, a commercial associates
- Directed personnel training and mentored team members to promote productivity, accuracy and commitment to friendly service
- Responded to customer needs through competent customer service and prompt problem-solving
- I closed the store managing cashier tills and safe deposits as well as security for loss prevention

#### Clerk/Cashier, 06/2010 to 10/2012

#### Sprouts Farmers Market – Tucson, AZ

- Natural Living: promote sales through out entire store for natural healthy living
- Manage inventory and placing various orders with different vendors
- Pursue education in vitamins and supplements to advise customers with various health goals

• Training in other departments: Produce, Grocery and Cashier

### Courtesy Technician, 03/2010 to 06/2010

Jiffy Lube – Mesa, AZ

- Greet customer, inform customers of recommendations, and cashier
- Basic introduction to vehicle inspections and courtesy services: wash windows, check tire pressures, and vacuum interior

#### **Security Guard**, 03/2008 to 03/2010

**Team Security** – Tempe, AZ

- Improve the safety and well being of patrons through: bag searches, I.D
- Checks, "pat downs", and patron ejections
- Received training in: note taking, radio etiquette, surveillance, and ejections as well as Guard Card
- Secured premises and personnel by patrolling property and monitoring surveillance equipment
- Responded quickly to incidents and assessed active situations for security concerns

### EDUCATION -

## Mesa/Pima Community College - Tucson, AZ

Automotive classes, Engineering class, Pre- Calculus, Health Class

#### **High School Diploma**

Skyline High School - Mesa, AZ

GPA: 3.45, Spanish Classes, Auto Technician Classes, Pre-Calculus Course

Full Stack Developer Boot Camp: Web Development, Expected in 01/2020

University of Arizona - Tucson, AZ

#### ACCOMPLISHMENTS -

- A3 Manual Drive Train and Axles
- A4 Suspension and Steering
- A5 Brakes
- C1 Automobile Service Consultant
- A6 Electrical/Electronic Systems
- A7 Heating and Air Conditioning
- A8 Engine Performance
- P2 Automobile Parts Leadership

- Training in security led to training new hires on proper procedures when dealing with various patrons and situations
- Security experience gave me confidence to stand up for the law and instruct patrons to do the same
- Experience at Sprouts Farmers Market cross training led me to take initiative to open a register to help customers through the checkout process faster
- Also, taking on other roles such as placing orders and loss prevention
- Hiring and training employees in different departments at PepBoys as a manager
- Becoming a certified technician allowed me to mentor new mechanics on the proper way to inspect and repair vehicles

## AFFILIATIONS -

- Diamondback Shooting Sports Training
- Automotive Service Excellence Certifications
- University of Arizona Boot camp

### CERTIFICATIONS -

- Armed Security Guard
- ASE A3 Manual Drive Train and Axles Certification
- ASE A4 Suspension and Steering Certification
- ASE A5 Brakes Certification
- ASE A6 Electrical/Electronic Systems Certification
- ASE A7 Heating and Air Conditioning Certification
- ASE A8 Engine Performance Certification
- ASE C1 Automobile Service Consultant Certification
- ASE P2 Automobile Parts Certification